Guide to the International Center for Transitional Justice (ICTJ) records, 1918-2020, bulk 1970-2020 RL.01304
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
- Geographic Files, 1918-2016; 1969-2016
  - North America/Caribbean, 1982-2009
    Each North American and Caribbean country contains journal articles and other publications, including ICTJ reports, related to governance, rule of law, political stability, truth and reconciliation, reparations, and human rights violations. Canadian Truth Commission, as well as the Mexican Attorney General's investigation of corruption, make up the majority of the North American/Caribbean records.
    - Canada, 1982-2009; 31 folders (Box 25)
      Legacy of Hope Foundation, institutional child abuse article, Six Nations Confederacy response to development in Brantford, workshops on telling the truth about Indian Residential Schools, Metis National Council list of indigenous groups seeking truth and reconciliation, University of Calgary Conference on truth and reconciliation, Chinese Canadians seeking reparations articles, ICTJ program overview, ICTJ trip reports, Assembly of First Nations legal proceedings, CIDA meeting reports, Canadian contributions to ICTJ, ICTJ meetings with the Assembly of First Nations, constitution acts, International Law of Human Rights in Canada, background reports on residential schools, legacy of residential schools project plans, task force on aboriginal languages and cultures report, Windsor Yearbook of Access to Justice--section about reconciliation, articles about Canadian government response to aboriginal schools, proposal for truth-telling initiative, discussion of TRC mandate for residential schools, Royal Commission on Aboriginal People report, Aboriginal Healing Foundation research reports, National Day of Healing and Reconciliation materials, TRC briefing documents, Canada TRC meeting, Human Rights Research and Education bulletin issue.
    - Canada Audiovisual Materials
      - Voices of Hope C.A.N, 2002 September; VHS (Box 125, Video-cassette RL01304-VHS-0073)
        Cincinnati Collaborative Project research findings video
      - Where Are the Children? Healing the Legacy of the Residential Schools, VHS (Box 128, Video-cassette RL01304-VHS-0171)
        Canada
    - Cuba, 2002-2003; 2 folders (Box 25)
      Articles and background about Cuba, analysis of abuse in Cuba.
    - Cuba Audiovisual Materials
      - A Patriot's Path to Democracy, 2002; VHS (Box 125, Video-cassette RL01304-VHS-0089)
        National Democratic Institute for International Affairs production
    - Grenada, 2010; 1 folders (Box 25)
      Evaluation of the TRC in Grenada.
    - Haiti, 1985-2011; 7 folders (Box 25)
      UN Security Council meetings, correspondence and reports on vetting with the UN Mission to Haiti, Pierre Kessler Paul's documents on seeking political asylum, ICTJ mission reports, Human Rights Watch report, ICTJ report on fighting impunity in Haiti.
    - Mexico, 2001-2008; 7 folders (Box 27)
      ICTJ trip reports, training by ICTJ in Mexico, CIDH documents, ICTJ research on truth telling and rule of law in Mexico, articles about truth telling in Mexico, news articles, report on catalyzing dialogue about transitional justice.
    - Mexico, 2002; 32 folders (Box 26-27)
      PGR Vol. 1-5.
    - Mexico Audiovisual Materials
      - Comision Nacional de los Derechos Humanos Mexico: Informe Especial sobre las quejas en materia de desapariciones forzadas ocurridas en la década de los 70 y principios de los 80, 2001 November; CD (Box 137, Cd RL01304-CD-0183)
      - Comision Nacional de los Derechos Humanos México: Informe Especial sobre las quejas en materia de desapariciones forzadas ocurridas en la década de los 70 y principios de los 80, 2001 November; CD (Box 137, Cd RL01304-CD-0184)
    - United States, 2005; 4 folders (Box 27)
      1898 Wilmington race riot report.
    - United States Audiovisual Materials
      Materials related to the Greensboro, NC massacre and truth commission.
      - The Guns of November 3rd, 1999; VHS (Box 128, Video-cassette RL01304-VHS-0176)
        Greensboro
      - Voices of Greensboro: Reflecting on the Tragedy of November 3, 1979, 2003; VHS (Box 128, Video-cassette RL01304-VHS-0169)
  - Central/South America, 1940-2014
    Each Central/South American country file contains journal articles and other publications, including ICTJ reports, related to governance, rule of law, political stability, truth and reconciliation, reparations, and human rights violations. Box 33 contains the legal sized materials for Chile and Guatemala.
    - Multi-regional, 1997-2004; 5 folders (Box 28)
      Centro de Derechos Humanos workshop, Argentina and Chile TRC reports, article on the defense of public apologies, article "Latin America's Smiling Mask."
    - Argentina, 1983-2009; 7 folders (Box 28)
      Partnership agreement with the Center for Legal and Social Studies project "Domestic Prosecution and Torture Prevention in Argentina," transition of democracy article, discussion of rights and human rights in Argentina.
    - Argentina Audiovisual Materials
      - Argentina copy, CD (Box 136, Cd RL01304-CD-0079)
      - De memoria: 1983: La transición democrática y el camino hacia la justicia (Vol. 3), 2005; CD (Box 136, Cd RL01304-CD-0073)
      - De memoria: 24 de marzo 1976: El golpe y el terrorismo de Estado (Vol. 2), 2005; CD (Box 136, Cd RL01304-CD-0072)
      - De memoria: La Primavera De los Pueblos (Vol. 1), 2004; CD (Box 136, Cd RL01304-CD-0071)
      - El Dia Despues, VHS (Box 125, Video-cassette RL01304-VHS-0093)
      - Esma: El Dia del Juicio, VHS (Box 125, Video-cassette RL01304-VHS-0092)
      - Guía de archivos de Derechos Humanos Mercosur y Chile, 2005; CD (Box 136, Cd RL01304-CD-0074)
      - Guía de archivos de Derechos Humanos Mercosur y Chile, 2005; CD (Box 136, Cd RL01304-CD-0112)
    - Brazil, 2000-2012; 13 folders (Box 28, Box 145)
      Project for technical cooperation, Latin American Network for Transitional Justice (LANTJ) meetings, creation of Brazil TRC meetings and strategy, articles about TRC, timeline of conflict and events, draft proposal of an assessment of transitional justice opportunities in Brazil, ICTJ mission assessment, Ministerio Publico Federal documents and investigations. Also includes UNDP Brazil Project documents from the Truth and Memory project.
    - Brazil Audiovisual Materials
      - 15 filhos: um documentário de Maria Olieira e Marta Nehring, 1996; VHS (Box 125, Video-cassette RL01304-VHS-0070)
    - Chile, 1986-2009; 25 folders (Box 28)
      Legal brief of incompatibility of Chilean law and international law, articles and declarations, international law after Pinochet article, report of the TRC, correspondence to and from ICTJ staff about speaking arrangements in Chile, Exonerados, article "The Pinochet Case: International and Domestic Repercussions," Aporte al Desarrollo de la Democracia seminar, newspaper clippings, Commission Etica Contra la Tortura, 1989 Programa de Gobierno, Ley no. 19.123, salud y derechos humanos articles, objective of the TRC, Chile Health Program, CNRR report of activities, Exilio report.
    - Chile, 1991-2001; 16 folders (Box 29)
      Historia de la Ley 19.074, 19.055, 19.128, 19.234, 19.582, 18.994, 19.740, Informe Mensual.
    - Chile, 1989-1999; 11 folders (Box 33)
      Seminar on returned exiles, newspaper clippings vol. 1-4, Memoria Ministeria de Justicia, Decreto Supreme no. 1005, Memoria Annal, Carta Informativa, Informe de Actividades, Camara de Disputados.
    - Chile Audiovisual Materials
      - 2 tiles PPT English Version Completa prelioniner-Chile, CD (Box 136, Cd RL01304-CD-0075)
    - Colombia, 1999-2014; 37 folders (Box 29-30)
      ICTJ program notes, correspondence about workshops in Colombia, UN reports, ICTJ capacity building workshop, articles about truth processes and conflicts, articles about the roles of gender in justice, WOLA conference report, Human Rights Watch article, UNCHR report on human rights situation in Colombia, international seminar on peace processes and transition, Colombia's Ley de Alternatividad and comments by NGOs, transitional justice recommendations, legal issues and suggestions for law modification, article "Voices of Girl Child Soldiers in Colombia," US Institute of Peace special report, ICTJ trip reports, articles about violence in Colombia, ICTJ transitional justice workshop, Bogota office strategic planning, ICTJ mission reports, restorative justice and peace symposium, Colombia extraditions notes, Swiss peace working paper assessing possibilities for further Swiss contributions.
    - Colombia Audiovisual Materials
      - The Authoritarian Spell: Alvaro Uribe Velez-First Year of Government, CD (Box 136, Cd RL01304-CD-0109)
    - El Salvador, 1993-2001; 6 folders (Box 30)
      Subject articles, justice for victims conference, laws and legal works, correspondence about an exploratory visit by ICTJ to El Salvador, proposal for educational events, US Institute of Peace report, recommendations from TRC.
    - Guatemala, 1981-2008; 66 folders (Box 30-32)
      UN report on Guatemala, subject articles, ICTJ training in international human rights law, Programa Nacional de Resarcimiento strategic plan for Guatemalan reparations, Dicatmen files, reparation program, MINUGA reports, correspondence about attending events in Guatemala, article "Guatemala: Memory of Silence," commission from the government of Guatemala to clarify past human rights violations and acts of violence, ICTJ mission reports, the historical memory project, consitution and penal code, peace accords, San Martin Jilotepeque committee, Rabinal research, project overview of post-war Guatemala, laws of reconciliation, SEPAZ documents and evaluation, FEMDEGUA report, El Deber de Resarcir article, press clippings, Guatemalan legal internship essay, reports on Guatemalan human rights and transitional justice, UN and ICTJ meeting about Guatemalan TRC, ICTJ case studies and lessons to be learned for Guatemala, DIGAP protection proposition, legal prosecution and penal code in Guatemala, report about the implementation of a national research program, ICTJ program reports, CIDH reparations rulings and the integration of those rulings, reports and correspondence about Guatemalan programs, reparations plan.
    - Guatemala, 1981-1999; 9 folders (Box 33)
      Órdenes Generales, CEH Memoria del Silencio.
    - Guatemala Audiovisual Materials
      - 1952-1954, Volume IV The American Republics Guatemala Compilation, 2003 May; CD (Box 136, Cd RL01304-CD-0110)
        US Department of State Foreign Relations
      - Fundacion de Antropologia Forense de Guatemala "Silent Tears Uncovering the Truth", CD (Box 137, Cd RL01304-CD-0181)
      - Guatemala Police Archives Project via Nicolas Guinard, DVD (Box 132, Dvd RL01304-DVD-0052)
    - Nicaragua, 2002; 3 folders (Box 32)
      ICTJ report "Dealing with the Past in Nicaragua," ICTJ trip report.
    - Panama, 2002; 1 folders (Box 32)
      Summary of the TRC final report.
    - Paraguay, 2005; 1 folders (Box 32)
      Paraguay truth commission.
    - Paraguay Audiovisual Materials
      - Los Archivos del Terror, 1992-12-22; CD (Box 137, Cd RL01304-CD-0174)
    - Peru, 1940; 1970-2012; 36 folders (Box 32)
      Peruvian penal code, ICTJ program report, disappearances, transitional justice lessons from Peru, Peruvian Navy personnel files, seminar from the Instituto de Derechos Humanos, lectures, Ministerio de Salud documents, Ministerio de Defensa documents, maps and report on deaths and disappearances, ICTJ recommendation for implementation in Peru, Fujimori case, CVR pamphlets, Oxfam: Saschacuy Tiempo, Estoy Recordando materials and buttons, CNDDHH and CVR backgrounder, correspondence about CVR, ICTJ trip agenda, ICTJ meeting notes.
    - Peru Audiovisual Materials
      - Instituto de Defensa Legal "sin rodeos", 2003-02-23; VHS (Box 123, Video-cassette RL01304-VHS-0013)
        Program no. 8
      - Instituto de Defensa Legal "sin rodeos", VHS (Box 123, Video-cassette RL01304-VHS-0014)
        Program no. 4
      - Coordinador Nacional de Derechos Humanos: Fujimori Webpage, CD (Box 137, Cd RL01304-CD-0177)
      - Instituto de Defensa Legal "sin rodeos", 2003-08-06; VHS (Box 123, Video-cassette RL01304-VHS-0001)
        program no. 23
      - Memorias de la Verdad, VHS (Box 126, Video-cassette RL01304-VHS-0095)
      - MTC Peru, 2003 July; Mini-DV (Box 139, Video-cassette RL01304-MDV-0045)
      - MTC Peru, 2003 July; Mini-DV (Box 139, Video-cassette RL01304-MDV-0047)
      - MTC Peru, 2003 July; Mini-DV (Box 139, Video-cassette RL01304-MDV-0048)
      - MTC Peru, 2003 July; Mini-DV (Box 139, Video-cassette RL01304-MDV-0050)
      - MTC Peru, 2003 July; Mini-DV (Box 139, Video-cassette RL01304-MDV-0051)
      - MTC Peru, 2003 July; Mini-DV (Box 139, Video-cassette RL01304-MDV-0060)
      - Musica Ayacuchana, CD (Box 137, Cd RL01304-CD-0189)
    - Venezuela, 2002; 1 folders (Box 32)
      TRC update.
- Reference and Reports, 1979-2014
  In addition to the hands-on work they do, ICTJ has a robust research unit captured in the Reference and Reports Series. These materials were collected by ICTJ and formerly housed in their Documentation Center and Library at their New York headquarters. The publications include annual reports from human rights NGOs as well as thematic publications about children and women in conflict, displacement, refugees, disappearances, human trafficking, judicial reform, economic issues, security and conflict analysis, genocide and torture, accountability and human rights.
  The Reference and Reports series contains publications, collected by ICTJ, of various human rights groups and organizations. This series is arranged into subseries: Global Publications and a set of geographic (by continent) files. The Global Publications subseries is subdivided into annual reports, human rights publications, and thematic publications, including: children and women; displacement, refugees, disappearances, and human trafficking; judicial reform, legal issues, economic issues and rule of law; security and conflict analysis; and genocide, torture, accountability and human rights.
  The remainder of the series is divided by continent: Africa, Asia, Europe, North America/Caribbean, and South/Central America. Organized within continental subseries with a multi-regional section first, followed by country files in alphabetical order. Country files are divided into thematic subseries.
  - Global Publications, 1996-2013
    Global publications includes an annual report sub-series containing annual reports from human rights NGOs, followed by publications aligning with major research themes from the ICTJ. The final two sections of this series are the human rights publications serials sub-series and the human rights publications sub-series. The human rights serials sub-series contains reports from NGOs, universities, and other human rights organizations that published more than two consecutive journals, newsletters, or bulltins. The human rights publications sub-series contains reports from NGOs, universities and human rights organizations, but are singular publications.
    Original electronic media is closed to use. Contact Research Services in advance to request the production of use copies.
    - Annual Reports, 1998-2007; 18 folders (Box 34)
      Includes annual reports collected by ICTJ from human rights groups. Groups include Lawyers Committee for Human Rights, Carnegie Council on Ethics and International Affairs, International Center for Human Rights and Democratic Development, International Council on Human Rights, Human Rights Watch, International Legal Assistance Consortium, Human Rights Center at University of California-Berkeley, International Crisis Group, Conciliation Resources, and the Association for the Prevention of Torture.
      Arranged chronologically.
    - Annual Reports: Electronic Media
      Coordinadora Nacional de Derechos Humanos annual reports CDs.
      - Coordinadora Nacional de Derechos Humanos Annual Report, 2001; CD (Box 137, Cd RL01304-CD-0171)
      - Coordinadora Nacional de Derechos Humanos Annual Report, 2002; CD (Box 137, Cd RL01304-CD-0172)
    - Children and Women, 2000-2012; 6 folders (Box 34)
      Includes reference material from the International Center for Ethnic Studies, the US Department of Labor, UNICEF, UN Office of the Special Representative of the Secretary General for Children and Armed Conflict, and the Global Protection Center Cluster Child Protection Working Group.
    - Displacement, Disappearances, Refugees, and Human Trafficking, 2003-2013; 2 folders (Box 35)
      Includes reference material from Linking Solidarity Against Enforced Disappearances, UN Department of Peacekeeping Operations, the Brookings Institution, and the Hafiza Merkezi Truth and Justice Memory Center.
    - Judicial Reform, Legal Issues, Economic Issues, and Rule of Law, 1997-2009; 6 folders (Box 35)
      Includes reference material from Transition International, the World Bank, Open Justice Initiative, Geneva Center for Democratic Control of Armed Forces, Due Process of Law Foundation, UN Security Council, UN High Commissioner for Human Rights, and the International Peace Institute.
    - Security and Conflict Analysis, 1996-2009; 7 folders (Box 35)
      Includes reference material from the US Institute of Peace, SIDA, UN Emergency Peace Service, Human Security Centre, UN Security Council, and the International Peace Institute.
    - Genocide, Torture, Accountability, and Human Rights, 1997-2009; 5 folders (Box 35)
      Includes reference material from the Coalition of International Non-Governmental Organizations Against Torture, Redress Trust, Center for Holocaust and Genocide Studies (Amsterdam), Center for Victims of Human Torture, and the UN Development Programme.
    - Human Rights Publications Serials, 1997-2008; 24 folders (Box 36)
      Serials from Combat Law Human Rights magazine, American University College of Law Human Rights Brief, Humanitarian Policy Group, International Development Information Centre, International Peace Academy, and the United States Institute of Peace.
    - Human Rights Publications, 1998-2009; 17 folders (Box 37)
      Includes human rights publications collected by ICTJ. Groups include the Aspen Institute Justice and Society program, UN Chronicle, Open Society News, International Council on Human Rights Policy, The Carter Center, Lawyers Committee for Human Rights, Interights Bulletin, Human Rights Watch, Harvard Magazine, International Bar News, Charles Stewart Mott Foundation "Mott Mosaic," FRIDE, Human Rights Media Center, Humanity in Action, and Foreign Affairs magazine.
    - Human Rights Publications: Electronic Media
      Institute for Justice and Reconciliation survey of reconciliation and truth CD and truth commissions in Uganda and Haiti CD.
      - Institute for Justice and Reconciliation Truth and Reconciliation Survey, 2001; CD (Box 137, Cd RL01304-CD-0179)
      - Joanna R. Quinn The Politics of Acknowledgement: Truth Commissions in Uganda and Haiti, 2003-09-05; CD (Box 136, Cd RL01304-CD-0081)
        doctoral thesis
  - Africa, 1992-2014
    The publications in the Africa series are from NGOs, universities, and other human rights organizations and include materials about children and women in conflict, displacement, refugees, disappearances, human trafficking, judicial reform, economic issues, security and conflict analysis, genocide and torture, accountability and human rights.
    Arranged alphabetically by country and then thematically within each country.
    - Multi-regional, 1997-2013
      - Multi-regional: Center for Democracy and Development publications, 1997-2004; 1 folders (Box 38)
        Center for Democracy and Development (CDD) publications.
      - Multi-regional: Children, 2005-2013; 1 folders (Box 38)
        "Talking to Arab Youth: Revolution and Counterrevolution in Egypt and Tunisia" book, Human Rights Watch report on West African regional warriors, Outside the Dream postcards.
      - Multi-regional: Displacement and Forced migration, 2007; 1 folders (Box 38)
        Refugee Studies Center Forced Migration Review magazine, Southern African Migration Project report on HIV and food security in Southern and Eastern Africa.
      - Multi-regional: Reconciliation and Transitional Justice, 1999-2011; 2 folders (Box 38)
        All Africa Conference on African principles of conflict resolution and reconciliation, Institute for Justice and Reconciliation report, International Peace Academy report, "Ni Guerra, Ni Paz" book about reconciliation in the Saharan region, FRIDE working paper on transition in Somalia and Uganda, African Union Commission consultation with African Union member states.
      - Multi-regional: Security and Crime, 1999-2008; 2 folders (Box 38)
        International Anti-Corruption Conference proceedings, The Critic magazine, Global Facilitation Network report, West Africa Weekly publication, UN Office on Drugs and Crime report, International Peace Institute report.
    - Angola, 2006; 1 folders (Box 38)
      FRIDE working paper on Angolan governance.
    - Burundi, 2005; 1 folders (Box 38)
      Global Rights Magazine: Global Rights Voices "Burundi's Land Crisis."
    - Cameroon, 2004-2006; 1 folders (Box 38)
      Nouveaux Droits de l'Homme informational publications for citizens about voting and fair elections.
    - Congo/DRC, 2002-2008; 1 folders (Box 38)
      Women's rights, Ituri Disarmament program assessment, and "Living with Fear" publication.
    - Ethiopia, 2000-2004; 1 folders (Box 38)
      Special Prosecutor's Report from the Special Prosecutor's Office and working paper on assistance to post-conflict Ethiopia. In Amharic.
    - Ghana 1992-2003, 5 folders (Box 38)
      CDD annual reports; CDD report of national reconciliation conference; CDD research paper about public opinion on reconciliation in Ghana; CDD workshop and research paper about military-civil relationships; CDD reports, newsletters and publications on Coalition of Domestic Election Observers report, Commission on Human Rights and Administrative Justice report, and reports on religion and politics in Ghana.
    - Guyana, 2003; 1 folders (Box 38)
      Guyana Human Rights Association submissions.
    - Kenya: Human Rights, 1997-2007; 2 folders (Box 38)
      Kenya Human Rights Commission reports and publications.
    - Kenya: Constitution of Kenya Review Commission, 2002; 1 folders (Box 38)
      Summary of the Constitution of Kenya Review Commission proposals, report of the Constitution of Kenya Review Commission.
    - Kenya: Truth, Justice, and Reconciliation, 2003-2014; 1 folders (Box 38)
      Transparency International Kenya newsletter about why Kenya needs a truth and reconciliation commission, Kenya Transitional Justice Network summary of the TRC, Amani Club Guidelines booklet.
    - Liberia: Criminal Justice, Legal Issues, and Security, 1999-2003; 1 folders (Box 38)
      Liberia National Law Enforcement Association review of the criminal justice system, Ministry of Foreign Affairs acts, International Crisis Group report, International Legal Assistance Consortium report.
    - Liberia: Peacebuilding, 2002-2005; 1 folders (Box 38)
      International Peace Academy report about civil society's role in national reconciliation and peacekeeping, the World Bank social development paper about community cohesion in Liberia.
    - Morocco, 2004-2009; 8 Volumes (Box 38)
      Summary of the final report of the Commission Nationale pour la Vérité, l'équité et la Réconciliation, bibliography of human rights violations in Morocco, annual report of the human rights situation in Morocco, protection of refugees, Informe final of La Verdad y La Responsabilidad Relativas a las Violaciones.